<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="troubleshooting">
	<title>Troubleshooting</title>
	
	<sect1 id="faq">
		<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
		<qandaset>
			<qandaentry>
				<question><para>iriverter jumps right to the "Complete" screen when I press convert.</para></question>
				<answer><para>You probably don't have all the fields of the jobs filled in correctly.</para></answer>
			</qandaentry>
			<qandaentry>
				<question><para>I get a "mencoder.exe has caused an error" popup.</para></question>
				<answer><para>MEncoder, on which iriverter is based, is sort-of unstable on Windows, so some videos may cause it to crash.</para></answer>
			</qandaentry>
			<qandaentry>
				<question><para>I can't see the video on my H300!</para></question>
				<answer><para>Make sure you have the correct firmware installed and that you are looking for the movie in music mode.  See <xref linkend="firmware" /> for details.</para></answer>
			</qandaentry>
			<qandaentry>
				<question><para>I get a "Video Not Support" error.</para></question>
				<answer><para>Try using the default video bitrate of 450 and audio bitrate of 128.  If that does not work, run the problematic video through the "Join Videos" job as that will rebuild the AVI header that may help it to be played.</para></answer>
			</qandaentry>
			<qandaentry>
				<question><para>The audio is out of sync with the video.</para></question>
				<answer><para>After the video starts playing on your iriver, rewind it about a second or two.  This tends to get everything back on track.  Otherwise, try lowering the video bitrate to 320.  If you still get problems with sync play around with the manual sync function of iriverter as documented in <xref linkend="sync" />.</para></answer>
			</qandaentry>
		</qandaset>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="other">
		<title>Other Places to Get Support</title>

		<para>If you have problems with iriverter, please feel free to contact the author, James Lee, at <email>jlee23@umbc.edu</email>.  Additionally, <ulink url="http://www.misticriver.net/">MisticRiver</ulink> has a great <ulink url="http://www.misticriver.net/boards/forumdisplay.php?f=106">video conversion support</ulink> forum.
		</para>		
	</sect1>
</chapter>
